Finding Aid for Kelsey Museum of Archaeology papers 1890-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Kelsey actively monitored a plan for the campus of the University, advocating strict adherence to its proposals, so that the campus would retain its beauty and dignity with the passing years. The donation of a bronze fountain by the mayor of Ann Arbor found a suitable campus location through Kelsey's efforts. His visions of continued growth led to contacts with Horace Rackham who contributed generously to the Near East Expeditions. Through his efforts, the Pendelton Library in the Michigan Union was built and stocked. Many scholarships and fellowships were established and underwritten by the benefactors he solicited. It was also Kelsey's idea to publish the Frieze Diary.
Kelsey sought to attract the best minds to the Latin Department and was tireless in his efforts to secure funds for scholarly projects which would enhance the reputation of the University. One of these projects was the Humanistic Series, to encourage scholars to publish manuscripts which would stand as singular contributions to scholarship and win international recognition. After an unsuccessful attempt to finance this plan through the Regents, President Angell advised Kelsey to see Regent Arthur Hill, Chairman of the Finance Committee. Hill was so taken with the idea, that he gave Kelsey a personal donation of $300 to get things started. The first volume of the Humanistic Series appeared in 1904. Philanthropist Charles Freer of Detroit, also impressed with Kelsey's idea, chose the Humanistic Series as the medium to make available facsimiles of his manuscripts to scholars. So close was their collaboration that Freer left a bequest to the University in order to continue publication in connection with his collections, even though the collections themselves were deeded already to the Smithsonian Institute in Washington, D.C.
Association with Charles Freer also brought to the University the Dattari Coin collection, an outstanding collection consisting mainly of Egyptian coins dated from just before the founding of Alexandria to the middle of the fourth century A.D. Other coin collections came to the University through Kelsey also and it was Kelsey's contacts through Freer which led to the acquisition of the great papyri collection.
Charles Freer and Thomas Spencer Jerome an alumnus of the University of Michigan, were close friends. Although it is not clear how Kelsey became acquainted with either gentleman, Kelsey's diaries reveal that he knew them well enough to have been invited to lunch at their villa in Capri, Italy in 1901. After Jerome died in 1914, Kelsey went to Italy in 1915 to oversee Jerome's estate, divide his library collection between the University of Michigan and the American Academy in Rome, and rescue his monumental manuscript on "Roman Morals", which he was writing at the time of his death. This manuscript was to be published by G.P. Putnam.
Returning to America by ship, Kelsey met Dr. David Askren, a missionary and physician, then working in the Fayoum district of Egypt; through him, Kelsey heard of the existence of rare papyri. Appointing Askren an agent for the University and working through Maurice Nahman, an Egyptian dealer in antiquities to whom Freer had introduced him, Kelsey was able to secure a number of rare and valuable papyri in 1920. These were divided between the University of Wisconsin and Michigan; however, Michigan's collection is considered even today to be the finest in the western hemisphere.
As a further word regarding Kelsey, Jerome and Freer, Kelsey assigned to Professor John Winter of the University of Michigan the task of readying Jerome's manuscript for publication. Working from Jerome's unfinished manuscript and detailed notes Aspects of the Study of Roman History finally was published in 1923. Kelsey's advice was instrumental in carrying out Jerome's bequest to the University to "further historical research" by establishing the Jerome Lectureship at the University and the American Academy in Rome. The Jerome Lectures bring outstanding classical scholars to Ann Arbor and Rome, bi-annually to deliver a series of lectures. Winter was selected to present the first Jerome Lecture. As a final note on Kelsey's relationship with Freer, Kelsey wrote to Charles Freer in 1904, asking that he consider giving a $500 Fellowship to John Winter; Freer did so, anonymously.
Kelsey's humanitarianism led him to assist other poor scholars as well by quietly asking benefactors for anonymous assistance to them. His efforts also crossed nationalistic lines. German Colleagues acknowledged Kelsey's efforts in securing private contributions after the war to continue their work on the great Latin Thesaurus. He aided in the work of the Near East Relief Committee after the Armenian Massacre: he was Secretary in the State of Michigan for the Belgium Relief Committee, whose mission was to feed and clothe the children in Belgium after World War I.
Kelsey also was an active participant in his church and was a dedicated family man. He married Isabel Badger in 1886, and had two daughters and one son. He returned to Ann Arbor after the 1926 expedition in poor health and intense pain, yet he managed to keep up his correspondence until he died on May 14, 1927. He is buried in Forest Lawn Cemetery in Ann Arbor.
Francis Kelsey left behind a remarkable series of contributions to the academic world in general and the University of Michigan in particular. His papers are an accurate reflection of those contributions and his many interests.
Robert H. McDowell 1894-
Born in Persia in 1894 and a native of Alexandria and Syria, McDowell graduated from Wooster, Ohio Preparatory School and then from Wooster College in 1915. He received a Masters and Ph.D. from the Ohio State University two years later in 1917. McDowell served as a Lieutenant in British Military Intelligence during World War I. He was the first Treasurer of the American Relief Committee in Iran in 1917 and the first Director of Near East Relief in Turkey after the war. McDowell became a Research Associate in Mesopotamian Studies at the Kelsey Museum and did field work in Tell Umar, Iraq and Seleucia and Tigris from 1935 to 1936. His published writings in the Humanistic Series focused on the results of those expeditions. He entered the U.S. Army in 1942 as an intelligence officer and was awarded the Bronze Star in 1945 for meritorious service in Yugoslavia. McDowell became associated with the history department at the University of Michigan in 1945 and resigned in February 1946 to take a position with the Federal Government in Washington, D.C.
Enoch Ernest Peterson
Enoch E. Peterson was born on September 24, 1891 in Liberty Pole, Wisconsin, and later moved with his family to Fargo, North Dakota. He graduated from the preparatory and college departments of Luther College in Deborah, Iowa in 1912 and taught Latin there, first to preparatory, and then to college students. He entered the University of Michigan in 1921 as a graduate student and earned a Master's Degree one year later. The University sent him to Edinburgh in 1923 to do special research under Sir William Ramsay, the distinguished Anatolian scholar, in preparation for proposed excavations at Antioch in Asia Minor, and he remained in Edinburgh until 1925.
During this same time, Peterson did extensive field research for the University of Michigan excavations, first under David M. Robinson at Antioch in Pisidia during the summer of 1924, then at Carthage in North Africa under Francis Kelsey in the spring of 1925 and finally under James Starkey at Karanis in Egypt during the 1925-1926 season. Kelsey was so impressed with the young man's aptitude for research and his qualities of leadership, that he recommended Peterson be appointed Director of the expedition for the 1927-1928 season. Peterson served in that capacity, and went on to oversee other University sponsored excavations in Egypt, Karanis, Dimé and Terenouthis until all operations were finally halted in 1935.
During this period Peterson developed a love for Egypt and the desert, and he would recall his experiences in that area with great pleasure. He devoted himself to field work. Peter - son's instincts and methodology led his team to successfully uncover an entire city of the Greco-Roman period, thereby permitting the study of daily life in an ancient city. In addition, numerous relics were positively identified and dated, enabling archaeologists to classify similar pieces whose exact origins and functions had heretofore been unclear.
Upon his return to the University of Michigan in 1935, he was appointed Egyptian Curator of the Museum of Art and Archaeology and taught laboratory courses in numismatics and other antiquities in 1938. He received an honorary Doctor of Letters from Luther College in 1941. Peterson succeeded John Winter as Museum Director in 1950, serving in that capacity until he retired in 1961.
During the post-Karanis years, Peterson also worked continuously and diligently to publish the results of his efforts in Karanis. In addition to his reports published in the Humanistic Series, Peterson gave many lectures on the subject, and wrote about the coins of Karanis with Rolfe Haatvedt, and on the topography and architecture of Karanis. Course 51, which he taught in the 1950's, incorporated the knowledge and experience accrued during the archaeological expeditions. Upon his retirement in 1962, the Regents named Peterson Director Emeritus of the Kelsey Museum and Lecturer Emeritus in Classical Studies. Peterson died in September 1978 in Fargo, North Dakota.
Louise Shier
Louise Shier, born in Detroit on September 28, 1906, attended high school there. She earned all her degrees at the University of Michigan: A.B. in 1927; M.A. in 1928; Ph.D. in Oriental Languages in 1933 and an A.M. in Library Science in 1936. Miss Shier started at the Kelsey Museum as a student, and remained to become Assistant Curator, Associate Curator and Curator until her retirement in 1977. She also served as Museum Director for a short time in the early 1970s. She contributed to an article published in the Humanistic Series by Professor Worrell, and wrote Terracotta Lamps from Karanis, Egypt which was published in 1978. Miss Shier was a member of the American Oriental Society, the Archaeological Institute of America, the American Research Center in Egypt and she served for a number of years as Secretary of the Women's Research Club of the University of Michigan. Miss Shier passed away in 2015.
John Garrett Winter
John Garrett Winter, first Director of the Museum of Art and Archaeology (since renamed the Kelsey Museum of Archaeology), was born in Holland, Michigan on February 14, 1881. He received the A.B. degree in 1901 from Hope College in Holland, and taught Latin and Greek there for two years. He earned the A. M. degree from the University of Michigan in 1904 and the Ph.D. degree in 1906. He taught Latin and Greek at Michigan, then in 1919 became Professor of the Latin Language and Literature and served as Chairman of the Latin Department from 1928 - 1946.
Francis Kelsey in his position as head of the Latin Department chose Winter to edit the manuscripts of Thomas Spencer Jerome, a former graduate of the University, whose generosity led to the establishment of a lectureship in classical studies. In 1929, Winter gave the first Jerome Lecture at the University and the American Academy in Rome. He was named Russell Lecturer for 1935- 36.
When the Museum of Art and Archaeology was established in 1929, Winter was appointed Director and served in that capacity until his retirement in 1950. He was also Director of Fine Arts (1928 - 1946), member of the Managing Committee of the American School of Classical Studies in Athens, and a member of the Advisory Council of the American Academy in Rome. He was a member of a number of professional and scholarly societies, including the Societe Royal Egyptienne de Papyrologie, the American Philological Association, (he served as President in 1944), the Internationale de Papyrologues, the Archaeological Institute of America, the American Association of University Professors, the Netherlands American University League, Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters, the Research Club of the University of Michigan and Phi Beta Kappa.
Winter wrote a number of books and articles, including Prodomus of Nicolous Stenos (1916) Life and Letters in the Papyri (1933), and Michigan Papyri (Vol. III) (1936). He was editor of the Aspects of the Study of Roman History (1923, Jerome's book) and served as general editor of the Humanistic Series from 1928-1950. Winter was noted for the citations, which he wrote and read at all commencement and other ceremonial occasions. John Winter died on March 23, 1956 and is buried in Arborcrest Cemetery in Ann Arbor.
The Kelsey Museum of Archaeology Papers document the administration of the museum from its founding in 1929 and the research and field activities of University of Michigan archaeologists and classical scholars dating back to 1890. The papers consist of files of Kelsey Museum director's and curator's and University of Michigan scholars closely associated with the museum or active in archaeological work prior to the museum's founding. The papers include extensive correspondence files; field notebooks, maps, photographs, reports, and other research material from archaeological expeditions; drafts of articles and books; teaching material; and administrative records
The Kelsey Museum Papers have been treated and described here as a single collection divided into a number of subgroups. In the collection guide prepared by the Kelsey Museum, these subgroups were treated as individual collections, each with a separate finding aid and box numbering sequence beginning at one. The largest subgroup by far is the Francis Willey Kelsey papers, totaling 66.5 linear ft. Artifacts from excavations conducted by Kelsey formed the basis of the Museum's collection.
Papers Kelsey Box #
Arthur E.R. Boak 1-3
Campbell Bonner 1
Orma Fitch Butler 1-24
Inst. of Archaeological Research 1-7
Thomas Jerome Spencer 1-20
Francis Willey Kelsey 1-156
Kelsey Museum 1-4
Robert H. McDowell 1
Enoch Ernest Peterson 1-8 217-224
Louise Adele Shier 1-9
John Garrett Winter 1
Carthage Excavations 1-15
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute of Archaeological Research.; University of Michigan Near East Research Expedition (1924-1934); Karanis (Egypt); Carthage (Extinct city); Archaeology.; Excavations (Archaeology)--Tunisia--Carthage (Extinct city); Excavations (Archaeology)--Egypt--Karanis (Extinct city); Excavations (Archaeology)--Turkey--Pisidia (Extinct city)
Contributors:
Boak, Arthur Edward Romilly, 1888-1962.; Bonner, Campbell, b. 1876.; Butler, Orma Fitch.; Jerome, Thomas Spencer, 1864-1914.; Kelsey, Francis W. (Francis Willey), b. 1858.; McDowell, Robert H.; Peterson, Enoch Ernest, 1891-; Shier, Louise Adele, 1906-; Winter, John Garrett, 1881-1956.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Maps.
- Arthur Edward Romilly Boak papers, 1920-1960; 1.3 linear feet
  - Topical Files
    Papers, 1920-1962 of Arthur Edward Romilly Boak, Professor of History at the University of Michigan (1914-1958); Henry Russell Lecturer, 1949-1950; Jerome Lecturer, 1951-1952; member of the University of Michigan Expedition to Karanis, 1924-1925 and 19311932; scholar in the field of Ancient History; Fellow of the International Institute of Arts and Letters and member of numerous other scholarly societies; author or co-author of eleven books; includes letters, notes, maps, focusing on the archaeological expeditions to Karanis, Dimé and Seleucia; Boak's involvement with the Institute of Archaeological Research; "Historiae" notes and illustrations for his book on World History: correspondence with Francis Kelsey on the papyri: and research notes and photographs of the papyri used in preparation of his article "The Building of the University of Michigan Papyrus Collection", published in 1959.
    - Archaeological Research, 1924; 1934-1941; 1943; 1945-1946; 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Alexandria, Wadi Museum [Kelsey], 1920; 1924-1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Boak Coin Collection (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Expedition-Papyrus, etc. [Kelsey), 1920; 1923-1924; 1926; 1930 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Kelsey Museum, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Lecture: Karanis excavations (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Karanis
      - Lectures (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Zoological and Biological material, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - No. 263, 250 A.D. Certificate of Pagan Sacrifice (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Excavations in the Fayoum Newsclips (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Karanis and Domitianus Notes (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Maps (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Historiae
      - World History Outline (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Illustrations for World History (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Material for short edition of Gioroth[?] (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Hagiographical Bibliography (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Index to 6th Century Hagiographers (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Isidoros Mss. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Hammurabi (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Nile Valley's Delta (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Prehistoric Outline of Near East (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Wolff-Byzantine Influence (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Rome in the Age of Scipio Africanus (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Military History (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Military History of the U.S. Notes (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Michigan Karanis Papyri (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Misc. papers' Scientific Club History (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Roman History-Illustrations (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Roman History-Abstracts (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Photostat Reproductions of the text of the Book of the Prefect (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Imperial Coin Portraits Prints and negatives (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Alumni University Lecture (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Phi Beta Kappa Address (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - International Institute of Arts and Letters, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Misc. Items
      - 1933, 1954-1955; 1960 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - University of Michigan Papyri Collection
    - Notes; pamphlets; notebook, etc. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - P. Mich. 645 Corrections and Correspondence, 1925; 1939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - British Columbia Papyri, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Association Internationale Papyrologie, 1950; 1952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Misc. letters, 1954; 1957-1958; 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Letters to Herbert Youtie, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Papyrological bibliography (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Index of inventory numbers (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Karanis Photostats (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Papyri from Baechies[?] (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Photos of fragments (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
    - Photos and text (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Misc. papyri photos (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Unpublished material (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Thesaurus Linguae Latinae, Vol V, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Additional Items
    - Fasti Anni Ivliani (photostats)
    - Photos of fragments, Ludwig Koener
- Campbell Bonner papers, 1920-1950; 0.5 linear feet
  Papers, 1920-1950, of Campbell Bonner, Professor of Greek Language and Literature at the University of Michigan (1912-1946); expert on ancient amulets and glass; scholar; member of many learned societies; author; includes letters and reports covering Bonner's work on gnostic amulets and glass; detailed correspondence with Francis Kelsey about the Papyri collection, and letters from John Winter describing his travels abroad in 1921-1922.
  - Topical File
    - A.A.U.P. Summer Session matte, R.O.M.A.1931, 1944; 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Amulets, 1930-1935; 1945-1946; 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Amulets, Gnostic Gems, etc., 1930-1932; 1934-1939; 1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - British and European Collections, 1930-1936; 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - British Museum, undated; 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hanfmann, George M.A., 1936; 1946; 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Kelsey, Francis W., 1921-1924 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Kelsey, Francis W. re: Papyri, 1920-1924 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Misc. Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Re: Papyri Records, Reports (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Seyrig, Henri, 1933; 1936; 1943-1945; 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Taylor, Gilbert, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Winter, John G., 1921-1922; 1924; 1928; 1947 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Classical Weekly-photos and sketches by L. Teholiz (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "Eros and the Lion"-bibliographical material (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Travel Notes (?) (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Orma Fitch Butler Papers, 1913-1938; 10.3 linear feet
  Most of Orma Butler's records contain correspondence, including many letters with Francis Kelsey between 1919 and 1927. However, only a small portion is arranged alphabetically and grouped as correspondence; numerous letters are scattered in subject files, such as the Dattari Coin Collection, Karanis expedition, Barosso wall paintings, and the De Criscio and De Priscio inscriptions. General correspondence about the museum illustrates its operation from the beginning and reveals an ongoing struggle to secure more funds, more space and more recognition. Subject files include reports, financial statements, and many inventory lists. In addition to correspondence the collection contains resource material consisting of articles and illustrations from various periodicals; manuscripts, including one submitted for Miss Butler's Doctoral Thesis; reprints; periodicals; and a large collection of photographs. Miss Butler divided these photographs into two sets: one consisting of several Italian cities and the other of works of art found in various Italian Museums. The latter set was grouped alphabetically, by subject. In arranging this collection, each photograph was assigned an identification number. Subjects are listed on the front of the folder and serve as a key in identifying individual photographs. A number of other papers from the Kelsey records and handwritten reports by Enoch Peterson, Director of the Karanis expeditions for nine years are incorporated into Miss Butler's files. There is a notation in the finding aid beside each file which contains Kelsey material.
  The Karanis expedition records consist of handwritten and typed reports, financial records, lists, charts and correspondence. multiple copies of "Records of Finds" were eliminated, since complete bound records are in the Range Area Room of the Museum. Also eliminated were "Loose Papers", a collection of typed copies of various lists which are included in other Karanis files.
  "SHA Material" was the term Butler used to describe notes and papers pertaining to her thesis, Studies in the Life of Heliogobalus (1908) based on the Scriptores Historiae Augustae, which recorded the lives of the Emperors from Hadrian to Numerianus. Only some of these notes and the manuscript of the thesis were retained.
  The "Biographical Section" of this collection is sparse. A few periodicals from Italy highlight events which took place when she was there in 1925-1926, and several University of Michigan publications include photographs of the campus and miscellaneous newspaper articles. A scrapbook of poems which she clipped from various sources completes this Section.
  This collection of Orma Butler's files is valuable as a reference source. It complements the Kelsey papers by showing the successful completion of many projects which were left pending at the time of Kelsey's death in May 1927; It also contains numerous documents showing the Provenance of Museum artifacts.
  - Section 1: Correspondence
    - Anschutz, Irma, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Antiquities Bought for Teachers., 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)